So here's the plan.
First I'm going to teach you a little bit about the scala programming language and you need that before
we can actually start writing Spark code in Scala.
So first things first if you already know Scala that's great you can skip this whole section but if
not stick with me to learn some of the basics.
All right let's learn Scala.
Just to set expectations you're not going to be a Scala expert at the end of watching four videos with
me.
So what I'm really trying to do here is just get you familiar with the syntax of the scala programming
language and introduce some of the basic constructs like how do I call a function in Scala.
How does flow control work?, What are some basic data structures I might use with Scala?  and just show
you enough Scala that it's not going to look scary and intimidating to you as we go through the rest
of the course.
So with that let's talk about scala at a high level first.
First of all, why learn Scala?
Well you've probably never heard of it before.
Maybe you have but you certainly probably don't know it.
It's mostly used for spark programming but it is uniquely suited for Spark because it's really structured
in a way that lends itself to doing distributed processing of data over a cluster.
You'll see why a little bit later on.
It's also what SPARK itself is built with.
So by learning Scala You'll get access to all the latest and greatest SPARK features as they come out
and it can usually take a pretty long time for these features to trickle down to a Python support within
Spark and it's also going to be the most efficient way to run Spark code itself.
So by using Scala you will have the fastest and the most reliable SPARK jobs that you can possibly create
.
And I think you'd be pretty surprised at just how much faster and how much more reliable the same spark
job rate in Scala is compared to say the same SPARK job written in Python.
So even though it might be tempting to go off and stick with the language you already know, learning Scala
is worth the effort and it's really not that hard.
Truth is the same spark code for Scala and Python look very similar to each other at the end of the day
.
Now scala itself runs on top of the Java virtual machine.
So it just compiles down to Java bytecode and gets run by the JVM.
So one nice thing about that is that you also have access to all of Java. If there's a Java library you
want to pull into your Scala code you can do that so you're not limited to what's in the Scala language
itself.
Actually reach down to the Java layer and pull up bits of Java that you want to use to.
And we'll do that later in this course for example for dealing with regular expressions and a little
bit more of an intuitive matter than you could otherwise.
Another key point about scala is that it is focused around what is called functional programming where
functions are sort of the crux of what we're dealing with.
Functions get passed to other functions and chained together in ways you might not be used to.
But this is really how SPARK works at a fundamental level.
You know we basically take the abstraction over a chunk of data and we assign it a function to do some
processing on that data and functional programming and Scala makes that very intuitive to do from
a language standpoint.
So with that let's dive in first a little bit of an administrative note.
So as we go through these introductory Scala courses I'm going to attach the actual source code files
to each lecture assuming we are on a platform that supports that sort of thing.
So you know feel free to just download those as we do in the videos.
Now if you did in the previous lecture download the entire big chunk of all of the course materials
all at once.
Same files are going to be in there too.
So if you want to just imported from wherever you'd save those course materials that's fine too.
Either way works so just don't get confused by that.
And with that let's take a look at some actual Scala code.
All right let's learn some Scala, shall we?.
So first thing I want you to do is go to the resources for this lecture and download the LearningScala1.sc
file that's the Scala workbook file, worksheet file and just download that wherever you download
your stuff in your Downloads folder and hit pause while you go take care of that please.
I'll stay here and wait for you.
Done.
All right let's move on.
So I've opened up the Scala IDE here by opening at my Eclipse shortcut on the desktop and what I want
you to do next is go to the file menu and saying new scalla project and let's call this project LearningScala
Shall we?
Just like that.
All right.
Now we do actually need a separate project for these worksheet files and all the reasons are complicated
.
Basically there's a conflict with a scala version that we used in the other project but just go with
it.
So go ahead and right click on that LearningScala project and hit import and go to the file system
and select whatever folder you download stuff from your browser into wherever you downloaded that
LearningScala1.sc file.
So for me that's the C downloads folder and we'll select LearningScala1.sc and just hit finish
and we should have if we open up LearningScala1.sc and  go ahead and double
click on that.
And here we go.
Now what we're looking at here is what's called a scala worksheet, it is kind of like a notebook in Python
and that you can actually interactively enter commands and see them evaluated right in line there.
So you wouldn't, you know go and write a real script this way but it's a good way to get familiar with
the language and just sort of experiment and try different commands and you can immediately see the
effect they have.
So what's going on here is you know you have a line of code and after you evaluate it which happens
automatically whenever you save the worksheet, it will tell you over here on the right the actual output
from the Scala interpreter that resulted from that commands so very good way to see you know what you're
typing in for code.
And the result that code has immediately Pretty cool stuff so let's just dive in and take a look at
some of the scalla code.
So you know every language has its variables right and variables can be mutable or immutable and mutable
means they can be changed.
Immutable means they can't be changed.
So in other languages that might be a constant variable or a final variable depending on the language
we're talking about.
Now in Scala they encourage the use of immutable variables as much as possible and those are called
'val' values with key word 'val'. So the syntax here for declaring a string value is a little bit unusual
.
Let's look at what's going on here.
So we have val.
I mean that is an immutable constant right.
Name this immutable constant.
hello.
It's going to be of type string.
And then I said it's value to Hola!.
So val hello.
Colon string equals value. So that syntax here val,
Meaning it's immutable.
Hello is the name of the variable colon and then the type equals whatever it is.
OK so that's how we declare an immutable value in Scala.
Now just to show you that it actually works let's change that to.
I don't know what's French for Hola.
Now watch out what happens when I hit control as to save it.
This actually all gets interpreted again, for she goes to the bottom of the file when I do that.
But if we scroll back up and see that announces Hello string equals bonjour and we can print out the
value of that string with a print line command.
So in Scala that's how you print out a line of output.
Print line parentheses hello, the value name will print out.
I'll put the value.
So there you have it.
Very simple strengthed very simple there.
Now if you although Scala encourages using immutable values, you can also use mutable variables as well.
If you need to sometimes you just can't get around it.
So if you need to do that you use the var keyword instead of val.
So here we have an example where we have hello there which is initially set to the value that we had
in hello, which you remember we sent to Bonjour.
So here we are assigning a variable called helloThere and assigning it the value hello hello referring
to this value up here that contains a string Bonjour. With me?, so far makes sense?.
If you've done any programming before you can probably follow along whats going on here.
So at this point the value of the helloThere variable is set to the string Bonjour. Sure?,  because thats what my
hello value was set to now because its a variable I can actually change it. So I can say helloThere
Equals hello plus the string "There!".
So I'm changing the value of helloThere from Bonjour! to Bonjour! There!. And you can see that when
I print that out indeed it does contain Bonjour! There!.
And just for fun we can change this back to hello up here.
Watch everything get re-evaluated when I save it and now it says hello there instead.
OK.
So you got it.
Basically there are val's that are immutable, var's that are immutable and the syntax and scala are
a little bit weird for declaring things you have the variable name colon type equals whatever you're
assigning it to.
OK so that's a little bit backwards for most languages.
Takes a little bit of getting used to it, but you'll get the hang of it.
All right so one thing I want to point out is that in functional programming we're using a lot of functions
and the danger of that is that if you have a function that quietly changes the value of something behind
your back that can lead to bugs.
Can lead to unexpected behavior.
So in functional programming languages like scala they really encourage the use of immutable constants
whenever possible.
So you want to be using val whenever you can instead of var.
So instead of using a mutable constant and then modifying it as you go, create new immutable constants
and build them up over time.
So here's an example of how that works.
So let's say I start off with an immutableHelloThere that is initially constructed from the concatenation
of whatever was in my hello string and the string "There!".
So initially I'm just putting Hello there into my
immutableHelloThere.
So you see here I'm actually doing the combination here on the right hand side here and putting it into
the final value where it will be changed.
Now you know you can change these together so you know let's say I want to add something else here.
Let's say I want a new val that's immutable.
More stuff and I can set that too.
Hello!There! plus.
Yeah. I'm just making this up as I go.
Right.
So let's see what that does.
So now I have Hello!There!yeah.
And basically you know I still have two values here one is called immutableHelloThere, one is called
moreStuff.
But I never change the value of
immutableHelloThere.
I never change the value of moreStuff after it was initially created.
OK.
So I kind of like always know what's in this this this symbol this name here it doesn't change and that
makes coding a lot more safe.
I need to go back to that value I can just refer to it by its original name and that's the best practice
for dealing with functional programming.
Now one thing I want to point out to notice that I didn't actually declare the type here Scala can and
actually implicitly figure it out in a lot of cases so I didn't have to say that immutableHelloThere
colon string because it knows that I'm sticking together two strings and that produces a string object
in return.
So in cases where there's really no ambiguity over the type scala can infer it for you automatically
and you don't actually have to do that colon type name syntax all the time.
OK.
Some other types of dealing with strings so far but there's all the usual suspects here.
If you want to integers as an integer type capital I ,we also have boolean values that can be true or false
lowercase are the key words there. If you want a single character you know basically a 256 one of 256
characters 8 8 bit value represent as an ASCII character you can use the carrot type double precision
floating point is double single precision is float.
And notice that we have the usual f suffix here indicating a floating point constant.
Scala is a little bit pickier than other languages in enforcing that use that.
So if you are using single precision constants make sure you remember to put that F at the end.
Double wide integers
is a long.
And we also have a 8 bit value called byte just like in Java that ranges from negative 127 to 127 and
you'll find a lot of these types are very analogous to the types in Java.
Reason being that Scala is built on top of the Java virtual machine.
So there's a lot of transparency between the two languages.
All right moving on.
Take a break now.
It's fine.
Go get a drink you know hit pause.
It's all right.
But let's talk about printing stuff out.
So a common thing you need to do in a language is output human readable stuff very simple to do in Scala.
If you just want to tack a bunch of stuff together you could just use the plus operator to do that.
So you can see I have a bunch of different types of information up here and I can just push them all
together with the plus sign here and create a big old giant strength. So print line is a mess and starting
with a string and then I'm concatenating on the number one, a boolean value, a character value,a double
precision value and a long value all together.
And when we print all of that out we get exactly what you would expect.
Here is a mess followed by all this stuff jammed together in the form of a string.
And that all this happens automatically.
All right.