Now sometimes you need to format numerical output and you might be familiar with the print style of
output in other languages, scala supports that too.
But the syntax is a little bit strange.
So what you do if you want to do formatting of that nature?. You need to prefix your string with the character
f and that expands to a little macro that says I'm going to use a printf style format within this string
.
So here we're saying print line f meaning that I'm going to be formatting the text in here somehow.
And I say pie's about that I have a dollar sign followed by the variable name that I'm going to be formatting,
followed by a percent sign and then the print format for how I want to display that.
So in this case I have a point free f meaning that I want to display a floating point value with three
decimal points of precision on the right hand side of the decimal point.
And if you're not familiar with that syntax you can go look up printf on the inter-webs and get
more details but a pretty common tool for formatting your output.
If you need to make sure that it's human readable and only has a reasonable amount of precision.
And if we run that we see Sure enough pi is about 3.142.
So that took the value of pi single precision which is 3.14159265, applied this formatting
string to it .3f and that made sure that we only have three decimal points places of precision
to the right of the decimal point.
Here's another example.
You can also use use the same trick for putting zero padding on the left of numbers sometimes that's
useful for sorting strings for example.
So in here we have the f prefix again dollar signed by the variable name.
Number one in this case it's a an integer which is the number one.
And we're using a percent sign followed by the formatting string which is 05d.
That means that it is a integer value and the 05 means that I want 5 places of precision with zeros
padding it in if necessary.
And the output from that is with 5 decimal places.
0 0 0 0 0 1.
OK.
All right.
Another trick we can do is actually substitute in variables as part of our string as they're being constructed
.
So for that we use the s prefix and then anything that's preceded by a dollar sign will just be interpreted
as a variable or a value name.
So we have this as a prefix I can use the prefix to use variables like $numberOne that will
pull in the integer value 1 up here, to $truth which should pull true and $letterA
should put in the character A and sure enough it works.
When we evaluate that we can use the s prefix to variables like one,two, a and you can also do fancier
stuff. you can do more than just reference values and values and variables.
Here's an example where we actually evaluate an expression.
So again that dollar sign means I'm about to evaluate something and it might be variable or value name
or it might be a whole expression.
So if you put something within curly brackets that basically says I got a little bit of code here that
I want to execute and you can put whatever you want in there.
It might be like a little tiny little function even but in this case we're just going to add one plus
two together and sure enough it works.
When we actually run that we get three. The s prefixes isn't limited to variables I can include any expression like
three. So dollar sign brackets one plus two just got converted to the value 3 inside that string
automatically. So very handy tools for producing output when you're printing stuff out or writing to
a file or what have you.
All right the next section gets a little bit weird.
So again if you want to rest your brain a little bit at that previous stuff sink in that's OK.
Well let's move on now if you're familiar with regular expressions they can be a powerful tool for pattern
matching strings and extracting information out of structured formatted data.
So let's say you have for example an Apache access log that has a very specific format you might use
a regular expression to extract fields out of that line of log information and we do that in this course
later on quite a bit actually.
So for example let's say I start with a string that has "To life the universe and everything is 42" and
we're gonna call that string
theUltimateAnswer. You read Douglas Adams you know what I'm talking about.
.
So the syntax for handling regular expressions in scala is really weird.
OK.
It's gonna blow your mind strange.
Nothing I can do about it.
Sorry to have to live with it.
What we have is this strange triple quote syntax followed by a dot R and that basically means, I want
to construct a regular expression out of the stuff in between the triple quotes.
So if you're familiar with regular expressions you'll know what this all means.
.* means extract a bunch of characters then look for a space and then we're going to look for
one or more numbered characters that's what the backslash D-plus means followed by a
bunch of other characters.
So basically this is saying go look for the first number in this string.
So I'm trying to suck out the 42 out of the string basically.
Now regular expressions is a whole topic in itself.
There are multiple O'Reilly books on the subject.
They can do some very very fancy some very complicated things with them.
So if you want to learn more about regular expressions go look on the Internet or try out the introduction
to regular expressions.
But from O'Reilly that's probably a good start.
But odds are you've seen these before and if you haven't you can usually find the one you need on the
internet. If you just look I'll provide you the ones you need in this course for log's for example.
So don't get too hung up on the syntax but the way Orson's galaxy is pretty weird.
So we have this this Regex that we created using this  .r operator here and what we're gonna do
to apply that.
It's really weird how this works.
You take that regex and you pass in wherever you want to put the result that you extract information
from.
So we're going to basically try to pull out that number 42 from the string and put it into a new value
called answerString.
And then we use the equal sign to say well I want to run this on the string called theUltimateAnswer
.
And you know the syntax of this really defies human logic.
You just have to kind of go with it.
You know  it's something about Scala but I just don't like.
But keep this work sheet around for word for reference so if you do need to do some regular expression
stuff later on you'll have this to look at because it really doesn't make intuitive sense at all.
Anyway what that does is it doesn't play that regular expression to the string extracts out that number
42 and sticks it in the string answerString.
Last thing we need to do is because that is a string but we really want to treat it as a number.
We can call toInt on that string and extract the integer value 42.
So toInt will convert any string to an integer.
And you know like you might expect there's also twoFloat or you know whatever else you might need.
Conversion operators are as well.
Notice I didn't actually have to put an
() .
Empty print.
See there.
That's not actually necessary.
And we get the answer we get 42.
OK.
So honestly this is about as weird as Scala gets.
If you made it through that Scala it's all downhill from here.
OK it's kind of easier as promised to with getting easier booleans work much as you would expect.
So if you just want to compare two things if one is greater than two.
Well no the answer is false.
One is less than two will give you true.
One thing that's a little bit ambiguous in some languages is what does one ampersand versus two ampersands
or one pipe versus two pipe do?.
You know what you're doing and or or comparison's you can do either one in Scala.
The only difference is that if you use a single ampersand both expressions get evaluated and then you
added together.
Whereas if you use a double ampersand that means that it can actually bail early.
So if isGreater were false it would actually not even bother evaluating isLesser at all.
And we go left to right you know only as far as it needed to.
So for performance you probably want to go the double ampersand usually but for safety a single one
might be better because you might have some expression in there that you assume gets run and might not
if you're using a double spread double ampersand.
Either way here you get the same answer.
You can't be greater and lesser At the same time.
So both of these provide a result of false. String comparisons also something that works differently
in different languages. In Scala it makes sense when you compare two strings using the equals equals
operator.
It actually compares the contents of the string and not the string objects themselves. so by setting one
string equal to Picard and I have another string called bestCaptain that's also set to Picard.
If I test Picard equal equal bestCaptain he compares the contents of those strings and says true.
Well you know I don't want to get all nerdy on you and debate the values of Star Trek Captain captains,
but believe that for an exercise to the reader shall we.
All right.
So that's less than one with scala a crash course some basic stuff here.
All we did was cover you know the syntax for declaring mutable and immutable variables.
We looked at some different boolean operators, some ways of printing out information applying regular
expressions
and you have what you need to do.
The large size here.
So make it real.
So while you're in here like I said you can just add in code here it hit save and it will get evaluated
right away so play around with it.
My challenge to you is to write some code that takes the value of pi doubles it and then prints it within
a string with three decimal places of precision to the right.
So you should have enough examples within this work sheet to do that pretty easily.
You know this isn't meant to be difficult but I just wanted to get your hands on with some Scala code
.
Actually get comfortable with the fact that yes you can write scala code yourself and actually make
it run and operate.
So please do that  exercise even though it does seem trivial.
It will be helpful.
So do that and we'll move on to the next lesson.