All right moving on this next topic is going to be a little bit easier a little bit more straightforward
just not talk about flow control and Scala.
So to get started, go ahead to the resources for this lecture and download the LearningScala2.sc
file wherever you download stuff.
And I will sit here and wait for you.
So hit pause and take care of that please.
All right let's move on.
So now I right click on LearningScala here, scala project here and say imports and go to wherever the
file system browse to wherever you download your stuff.
For me that is it's
for me that is C downloads and select LearningScala2.sc and had finished to import that into our
LearningScala project and double click on that and you should see this.
So let's just talk about flow control you know how we control the flow of our code in Scala, all
pretty intuitive.
You know there are a few syntactical differences from other languages but by and large you should look
very familiar to whatever language you're already familiar with.
So for example you can use if else syntax.
If one is greater than three print 'impossible', one isn't greater than three.
Else
Print line that world makes sense and sure enough that will output 'the world makes sense'.
Now I could also put brackets around this if I wanted to make it more than one line that's OK.
You know you see that down here where I'm actually splitting it out to be a little bit more readable
.
Often spark code.
You see people jam things on to one line just because they can and that's kind of a common attribute
of functional programming I'm afraid.
But either way works.
So that's fine.
There is no elseif OPERATOR So you'd have to actually do another.
You know elseif that if you want it to and that's all there is to that if an else says the way you
would expect.
Now matching.
So let's say you have like a switch statement another in other languages where you have evaluated want
to like have different cases, where you do something different depending on what value that that variable
has.
So in Scala that's called a match statement so and so the switch we use match.
Other than that pretty similar.
So let's say we start with a constant value,
Number.
That's the number three.
We can set a number match with the syntax here.
So I want to match on the value of number and for Case 1.
She had this sort of like equal sign greater than thing that sort of says you know associate this function
with that case so I could actually be a whole expression if I wanted to.
But in this example we'll keep it simple.
So in case one we're going to map that to print line one case two will be mapped to print line.
Case 3 will be mapped to a print line 3 and then this underscore is basically your default area to catch
all case here.
So case underscore meaning it's something that's not one, two or three will print line or
something else.
But in this case our number is three.
So it falls through to the case 3 and prints 3.
Which indeed works.
So again you know there's nothing really complicated going on there.
Just like a switch statement in other languages with a syntax a little bit different syntax a little
bit different we have match followed by the value name.
Here it's a little bit backwards from other languages and we had a little mapping operator here equal
or greater than to actually map cases to what you want them to do.
So that's the syntactical trickery there for loops.
Nothing special about them.
Well little bit syntactically So look at what's going on here.
We have a for loop  1 to 4.
So basically we want to iterate through the values 1 through 4 inclusively.
The only weird thing here is it's a little less than Dasch syntax here and that is basically a range
operator in Scala.
So that says I'm going to take the value X within the range of 1 to 4 and it's going to create you know
a list of 1 2 3 4 and iterate through that.
In this for loop so people will take here the square of each value.
So for each value one through four and multiply by itself and print the results and we see 1 times 1
is 1, 2 times 2 is 4, 3 times 3 is 9 and 4 times 4 for 16.
So the for loop syntax itself is exactly what you would expect.
But we have this new range operator here that something new.
So remember that's how you specify a range of values in Scala.
While loops absolutely nothing interesting there it works exactly the same as other languages so let's
say I start with the x variable set to 10 and want to iterate through this while x is greater than or
equal to zero. While I subtract 1 for it as I go print the values so you know there's really nothing
fancy there at all it is exactly what you'd expect.
We start with 10 and as we print the value and then decrement it will keep on going untill I hit 0.
So 10 9 8 all the way down to zero.
Just like in any other language and just like we have while loops we can also do do while loops also
just like in any other language.
There's really nothing scala special here going on.
We have basically starting with the value 0.
Do print the value incremented by 1 and do that while X is less than or equal to 10.
So instead of counting down from 10 to 0 we're gonna count up from 0 to 10 using a do while loop.
Again if you have any prior programming experience at all.
I'm sure you've seen this all before and there's really nothing special about it when it comes to scala
.
Works this way you think.
Now one thing I want to talk about those expressions in Scala And one thing that is a little bit different
is that we have a block code like this.
Let's say I'm starting with a value of x equal to 10 and then I'm going to add 20 to that.
Now in other languages that wouldn't actually do anything because we're not actually returning anything
from that expression but in Scala.
This has an implicit value so whatever the last expression is will be what this expression as a whole
is set to.
So I can actually take this expression and use that as the value 30.
So take a look at this.
I can say print mine this expression Galaxie was 10 x plus 20.
That expression gets evaluated and the number we're left with at the end is 30.
So this all gets translated into the value 30, which actually is what gets printed out here.
OK so we're trying to touch on some aspects of functional programming here where expressions can actually
be used as values of their own.
OK so that takes a little bit of wrapping your head around so stare at those two lines a little bit
longer and make sure that sinks in for you.
OK now just get your hands dirty.
Simple example here you probably see this on a lot of sort of simple job interviews to print the Fibonacci
sequence and whatever language you want.
In this case I want you to do it in the scala programming language.
Not hard.
All you have to do is write a little loop that goes through the numbers 0 through 10 and the expected
output should be something like this where every time you go through the loop you're adding in the sum
of the two numbers before it.
So basically you need to write a loop that keeps track of the previous two values sums them up as you
go.
So little exercise in some flow control and doing some looping in Scala.
Therefore you have at it and have some fun with it so I just wanted to get your hands dirty.
And again just get some confidence that you can actually write Scala code that runs. All you've to do
is write your code in here and every time you hit control as to save it will get evaluated for you and
you'll see the result right alongside your code.
So give that a try and see how it goes on to the next lecture.