Moving on, like I said Scala is a functional programming language.
So now it's time to talk about functions which are obviously very important in Scala.
So go to the resources for this lecture and download the LearningScala3.sc file.
Hit pause while you take care of that.
And just like before we're going to import that into our project as well.
So again right click on LearningScala project or the import a file system and select the folder where
you download your stuff to whatever that might be
and select LearningScala3.sc
finish, and you should see it here and your project. Lets double click that and take a look.
Should it look like this.
All right.
So let's talk about functions in Scala.
Very important lesson here.
Like I said functional programming is kind of building blocks of it.
So syntax for a function in Scala looks like this.
Start with def which basically means I'm declaring a function of some sort followed by the function
name. In this case squareIt, I making a function that just squares some value.
And the syntax again is backwards from what you might expect from other languages. So we start with a
parameter x that is an integer type and we would say that is x colon int and then the return value of
this function is an integer as well.
So we have another colon after that function named declaration in the parameters that is followed by
the type that is returned by the function.
So again this is totally different from what other languages might do.
Usually you would see int squareIt int x, instead in Scala squareIt x int and int.
So just take some getting used to but make sure you understand what's happening there.
So again def means we have a function followed by the function name or parameters which have a colon
that specifies the type of each parameter.
And then finally another colon followed by the type that is returned by the function.
And then another thing it's a little bit different is that we have an equal sign between that and the
actual brackets for the function because we're basically taking this expression and assigning it to
the squareIt  name.
OK so we'll be different there too.
But inside all we're trying to do is say X times x.
And again this is expression's remember from the previous lecture that we don't have to actually explicitly
return anything whatever the last value computed in that expression is what gets returned.
So this is all we need for a function that actually squares a value.
So let's take a look again.
squareIt takes in an integer returns an integer and it applies this expression to it x times X to actually
get the square.
Now we can do something similar here for cubing.
Again def cubeIt takes in an integer x returns an integer and uses the expression X times X times X
to compute what gets returned.
So let's see it in action with the print line.
squareIt(2), you just call the function like you would in any other language that we'll return four.
Similarly cubeIt(2)
will give 8 because you cube does 8 and 2 square is four.
All right.
Nothing too crazy.
So kind of makes sense right.
Things get a bit weird now.
So I remember I said before up here we're basically assigning this expression to that function named
squareIt.
So basically every function in scala is kind of it's own little object and you can pass these functions
around to other functions like they are objects themselves.
So that makes a lot more sense with an example here.
Let's make a new function called transformInt.
And what this function does is it will take a function to transform an integer. Could be any function
and apply that to some integers so our parameters here in this example are going to be an X which is
an integer that we want to transform followed by a function that transforms an integer to another integer
.
So we're taking it here as a parameter a function that expects as input one parameter that is an integer
and returns an integer.
And that's what the syntax here means takes in an integer and it outputs an integer as its result and
the return value of this function itself is an integer set equal to f(x).
So we're going to take the function f passed in and pass in the parameter x that was passed in and what
gets evaluated is that function f apply to that value X. So let's let's see how that works.
So for example we can call it transformInt the value 2 and the function cubeIt.
So this will pass in value to the X and the function Cuba to F..
The function will then take the function Kubit and pass in X to that and return the results.
That gives us back 8 because that will pass in 2 to the cubeIt function and return 8 with the results
and there it is.
Now for example we could change that to be squareIt and let's just make sure it works save.
Sure enough we get for now because now I'm passing two to the squareIt functions so you know you to
take a little break here and make sure that sinks in.
This is kind of the very fundamental and very important concept of functional programming that you can
pass functions around as parameters themselves.
OK.
I mean other languages this is still possible to do but you don't see it as often.
Ok so very important that you understand how that's working.
So stare at these little lines of code here.
Make sure you understand what's happening there before you move on.
OK.
Now you don't even need to have a separate function declared for this trick to work.
You can actually declare these functions in line as well.
And if you've worked with me on my other Spark class in Python This is very similar to how a lambda
function in Python works.
It also goes by the name of anonymous functions or function literals is a popular term in.
But you're gonna see a lot of this so make sure you understand the syntax of what's going on here.
So here I'm calling transformInt and instead of passing in a named function, that right here declared I'm just
passing in the expression itself.
So I don't even need to have a separate function at all.
I can say I'm going to pass in the parameter 3 and I'm gonna pass in this expression that takes in a
value X and transforms it using the expression X times x times X and this becomes my entire function
definition that I pass in to that function.
So instead of having a separate cubeIt function, I can embed what cuebeIt does just right here within this
call.
So this is perfectly valid syntax in Scala.
I can say I have some value X that gets transformed using eq. greater than 2 x times x times X and that
actually works.
You can see here that if I take it pass the value three to transformInt and I pass in this function
X gets transformed to x times x times x.
It actually works.
It will pass in 3 into X and execute that function on it to get the number 27 as a result.
OK let's look at it again.
So here's another example.
I'm using the same transform that just takes as parameters some integer and some function.
And in this case the function.
The only requirement is that transforms an integer to another integer.
I'm taking X and transforms it to X divided by two.
So in this example ten gets transformed into 5 that way.
OK one more time.
We can do a more complicated expression here.
So instead of just a simple one liner we can actually do a multi-line expression as well.
And in this example we're about to take the value 2 and pass into this function that transforms X into
this expression.
It actually does a couple of different steps.
It takes the value of y that's equal to x times 2 and then squares that resulting value from that
becomes the end result of that expression.
So we take to assign y to 2 times 2 which is 4 and then we multiply by times like 4 times 4 to get 16
.
And that is indeed what we get back.
So make sure you understand what's going on there.
You are going to see this syntax a lot in the world of Scala and in the world of spark in general.
So very important I understand that syntax.
It's pretty easy to eyeball it but you need to get a really intuitive understanding of what's going
on that's that's important.
OK so let that sink in and once it has sunk in I'll give you a little bit of a challenge here.
So a very simple exercise here.
Every string has a  .toUppercase method.
You can call it just transform the contents of that string to uppercase characters so play around some
functions write a function that actually converts the string to uppercase and try it out and actually
execute that function on some strings of your own.
Make sure it works and then actually get rid of this separates, the separate function entirely and do
it in line just like we did here with anonymous with function literals.
OK so I want you to try both doing this with a named separate function that's defined and also with
the function literal.
You just do in line.
So go do that to get some practice with functions and hey when you're done you can say you know functional
programming.
Congratulations.
That's something for the resume.
All right let's move on to our final lecture on our Scala bootcamp series