All right we're down to our last lecture in our scala a crash course here.
This one's going to be about data structures and it's a very important lecture.
We use these a lot.
So don't skip this one if you don't know them already as before go to the resources for this lecture
and please download the LearningScala4.sc file.
I'll wait for you.
Hit pause while you go take care of that.
And when you have that go on as before to to the to right click on the LearningScala project and say
import file system browse to wherever you download your stuff
and select the LearningScala4.sc for it.
The file open it up and you should see a little something like this so let's talk about what's going
on in here.
OK so a really common data structure you've seen in scala is called a tuple and you know you see this in
Python and some other languages as well.
Basically it's a collection of stuff that is treated as its own objects so we can make basically this
immutable list is how you can think about a tuple with a list of objects that you cannot change once
they've been created.
Very common in Scala.
So how do we declare one.
You're putting in parentheses and separate the contents of the list by commas.
So for example we can create a tuple called captainStuff that contains the strings Picard Enterprise
D and NCC 1701 So maybe this is a tuple that represents information about a Star Trek captain and
contains individual fields that have different information about that Captain.
So sort of an easy way to pass around you know semi structured data as its own entity and if you print
that out you can see that gets converted to the string that is you know the same syntax with in parentheses
the different contents of that tuples separated by commas.
captainStuff itself is a single object but it contains three different values.
These three different strings here so that is a good way to sort of stuff different bits of information
into one thing which comes in handy a lot with Spark as you'll see later on.
Now how do I get stuff out of it.
So let's say I want to extract values out of that tuple.
Well the syntax here again with scala is a little bit weird.
What you do is you put a dot after the tuple name and then underscore and the number of the field you
want to extract, and the thing to remember is that it is a one based index so the first value is number
one.
The second values number two,the third value
number three ,a lot of other things in computer science you start counting at zero.
This is not one of those times returning with one here.
So for example if I print captainStuff dot underscore one that extracts the first field of my table
which contains the string Picard, dot on each score
gets the second one which is that apprized daughter and score 3 gets the third element of that tuple
which is NCC 171 D  with me so far.
Nothing too challenging here but again you just have to get used to the syntax.
Now a special case is a key value pair.
Basically a tuple that contains two things.
And often you'll use this as sort of a key value mapping.
So let's say I want to create a tuple that represents a captain and the ship they command.
I could use this syntax to do that.
That will just create a tuple that maps Picard is the key to the value.
Enterprise D and all that does is give me back a tuple that contains a Picard and Enterprise D.
I could have declared it the same way as I did up here just by having it within parentheses separated
by a comma.
But this is sometimes a more readable format that sort of implies to the reader of your code that you
are in fact associating a value with a key here and that's your intent of creating that tuple.
You would dereference it the same way you would any other tuple picardShip  underscore 2 to
extract the value from that key value pair, because it's a second element and give you back Enterprise D,
whereas on a score one.
Let's try it would give me back the key which is the Picard.
Scroll back up to where we were where we are now.
Think about tuples they don't have to all be the same type.
You can actually mix and match different types of data within a tuple.
So here's an example where you have a string, an integer and a boolean all jammed into one tuple and
that's a perfectly ok thing to do.
Comes in handy sometimes.
So that's tuples.
Moving on take a little break you need to let that sink in.
Review it.
Or good.
All right lists are a lot like tuples but it's an actual collection object so it has more stuff you
can do to it, a bit more. Will get more heavyweight but a little bit more flexible.
So kind of like a tuple you can declare a list.
That's just a list of comma separated values here and under the hood it's got to build a singly linked
list to represent that information.
So here we have a shipList value that is a list of enterprise defined for deep space nine. So four different
ships from four different Star Trek series in this example. And the syntax of dealing with lists is different
than a tuple.
So for example if I want to extract a value from that list I can just use parentheses and then the field
number I want to extract.
So now in this case we're not starting with one we're starting with 0.
OK so you've got a growing number that very easy to make bugs around this stuff.
In this case shipList one will go extract the zero based element of the list at once so we go 0 is
enterprise ,1 it's defiant shipList(1) one gets me back defiant.
OK.
I know it's confusing but it's something you just have to remember with Scala.
Now Dot head will give you the first element of the list.
Tail will give you all the remaining elements of the list after the head.
OK so in other languages tail might return the last element.
That's not how it works here. Tail gives you actually list a sub list of the list that just excludes
the first element and sometimes that's useful if you're iterating through a list.
You need to extract one item and then you know keep working with the remainder of that list in the next
iteration.
OK.
Now let's say I want to iterate through an entire list and do something to every value within it.
That's something you need to do pretty often.
So remember that that range operator we introduced when we talked about flow control.
Well same trick applies to lists so we can say for ship and shipList and that will actually produce
a range and iterator that goes through every ship in the shipList assigns it to the ship variable and
get printed each ship one at a time that way.
So this code here again the key is this little range operator here that will go through the ship list
to extract each individual element into a new value called ship that we can then print out within this
expression so that will go through and print out each individual ship and our ship list.
More fun with lists here.
We can also use the map function to actually transform a list using some expression.
So Let's take a look what's going on there.
Let's say I have my ship list of ship names enterprise, defiant, voyager and deep space nine. I can call
dot map to actually apply an expression, some function to every element of that list one at a time
.
So in this case I'm actually defining a little function in line that takes a string called ship and
maps to ship dot reverse which just reverses the the characters in each string.
So what that does is say I want to take this function that reverses a string and map that to the ship
list and return a new list called backwardShips that contains the backwards names of all the ships
.
OK so I stare at that line for a little bit until it sinks in and the output is exactly what we want
So we have a list of all the ships with their names backwards.
OK.
So that's what the map function does.
It just supplies some function that transforms each element of the list into a new list.
OK.
And we can go through and print out those results to just using that same trick with the range operator
there to print out the results.
And sure enough we get the backwards versions of each ship name printed out one at a time.
OK with me so far.
OK so that's that's mapping.
That's the map function mapping sound familiar map reduce.
Same concept same exact concept.
The only difference is that we're not actually doing this in a distributed manner.
We're just using Scala's built in operators on the list to actually map one list to another.
Now I said map reduce, can talk about map without reduce then sure enough there's a reduce method on
list as well.
So just like we can use map to apply a transformation to every individual element of a list we can
use the reduced function to actually combine the contents of a list together.
So here we can start with a numberList just a list of the numbers 1 2 3 4 and 5. If I can call reduce
on that list with a function that tells how to combine these things together.
So basically what reduce does is it goes through each list and as it gets
each pair of items, will use the function we provide to combine them together.
So basically we're saying as new values come in from the list add them up.
So as I get to values that are processed together I've got to add them up take that result add and then
add value take that resulted in the next value and so on and so forth until we're done.
So basically this is a way of saying I want to take the entire list sum up all the values and give me
back the result.
And what that does is iterate through the entire list, one pair of  values at a time.
So it takes one plus two says that's three three plus three is six, six plus four is 10 and ten plus four is 15,
using that reduce operator that reduce function we provided.
And sure enough the answer we get back is 15 and we can print out that result.
Sure enough 15 and hey that's map reduce you know the only difference is that in a real mapreduce
application you would be using functions that actually work on a cluster.
Same concept though filter.
Also it can be used and you know if you've looked at Spark or mapreduce before that might also look familiar
you can actually use that to create a sublist based on some filter function you define.
So in this example we're gonna say I have a new class called iHateFives and I'm going to take my numberList
that contains numbers 1 2 3 4 5 and apply a filter that tests to make sure that X does not equal
5.
So I have in here a little inline function function literal if you will that takes an integer x and
tests if x is not equal to 5 and that boolean results of that function will determine whether or not
that individual list element survives and gets passed into the resulting lists what goes on here.
We start with 1 2 3 4 5.
We apply this filter function to it which will allow everything but the 5 to pass through.
And you can see that we end up with the list 1 2 3 4 and  5 has been excluded.
Do the same thing again here a little bit of a more compact syntax here that you often see.
Same idea but here we're using a little bit of a syntactical shortcut.
You can actually say in a function literal underscore to just say whatever it is is not equal to 3.
So that is sort of implicitly removing this X transformed to X and just simplifying it down to hey I
know I only have one parameter coming in.
I want to take that parameter whatever it is and just compare it to three.
OK and you can see that works just as well if I apply this filter function that makes sure that each
element represented by that underscore is not equal to three is all that passes through that I end up
with 1 to 4 or 5 where the 3 has been omitted.
So you know you do see this a lot in Scala where we have these you know people that want to save keystrokes
at the expense of readability but you need to understand that when you see it.
Now SPARK has its own map reduce and filter operations that can actually happen in a distributed manner
.
The only difference is that we'll be not operating on list structures but something we call RDD's
but we'll get to that later.
But same exact concept.
So if you understand how this map and reduce function , this filter function worked hey you understand
map reduce now and you also understand a good part about how SPARK works.
It's all the same idea.
It's actually not that complicated.
A few more or less tricks here.
Let's say I want to concatenate two lists together we have are one two three four five list numberList
and I want to concatenate a new list called moreNumbers that contain 6 7 8, the plus plus operator will
combine two lists together and that gives us back the combined listWwonder if you put 5 6 7 8.
Ok a few more tricks.
It has a.
Every list has a dot reverse method that will give you the reversed list.
So five four three two one.
It has a dot sorted method that will return a sorted version of that list.
So here I took my reverseList those five four three two one called Dot sorted on it and then returns
and you sortedList that's back to 1 2 3 4 or 5.
Let's look at distinct.
So let's say I take my number listin append itself number list plus plus number lists and I get one
two three four five one two three four five.
If I just want the distinct values in that list I can call that distinct and just get back to you three
or four or five because those are the numbers that only appear once.
OK.
So we also have a max function that will find the maximum value in the lists.
Sum will sum them all up if they are numbers that can be summed.
And I also have a dot contains function that can be used as a quick test to see if a list contains a
given value.
So I hate threes where we filtered out the number three contains three will return false because it
has everything but three.
All right that's less I want to take a break here let it sink in because we want to move on to maps
now.
All right maps maps just like maps in other languages sometimes are called dictionaries.
Basically there are a lookup table of given keys to values so the way to declare a map in Scala something
like this.
So let's say I want to create a map that maps starship captains to the ship they commanded.
So here we have a map of Kirk maps to enterprise where this Dasch greater than signs syntax mapping
keys to values here.
Picard associate with Enterprise D ,Cisco the Deep Space Nine and Janeway to Voyager.
And we can actually do a look up very simply here by using this print to see parentheses key name  here to extract
the value associated with that key so ship map Janeway returns Voyager.
OK.
Very easy to use.
Now one complexity is that when you're dealing with maps you need to deal with missing the missing keys
right so what if I did like Archer.
OK.
That wasn't in my list of original captains in my list of keys for this map.
So what happens if I try to extract Archer Well that shouldn't generate an exception.
So one way to protect against that is to make sure that the map actually contains that we're looking
for first.
So if I do that test I can say shipMap contains Archer that will return false because that map does
not have a key for Archer.
And at that point I could say well I know that he doesn't exist so I'm not going to try to extract the
value for that key because I knew that would lead to an error.
Another way you can deal with it is by using this Try syntax.
So you know just like try exception block or or try catch blocks in Java.
Similar concept there.
Well we're gonna do is use this utility try function that's built into Scala to actually extract the
value for Archer from ship map.
And what's going to happen is that's going to generate an exception because there is no key for our
tranship map.
But instead of erroring out we're going to wrap it in this utility try so it catches an exception get
or else says I want to actually get the value of this expression here.
But if it generates an exception Here's my fallback value of unknown.
And if I go ahead and execute that you can see that when I try to use shipmen Archer that does generate
an exception getOrElse handles that exception and returns the key string.
Unknown in that case so that's a safe way of accessing a map where you're not sure if the key is actually
in it or not.
All right.
Those are all the main data structures that we need to deal with with Scala.
There are others you know and we'll maybe touch on one or two more of them as we go through the course
.
Obviously there's a lot more to Scala than we've talked about here we haven't even really gotten into
object oriented Scala and some of the more mundane details of the language that might come up from time
to time.
But as new concepts come up through this course that you might need I'll introduce him to you as we
go.
This is all you need to get started.
So these are the basics of Scala.
If you do want to learn more there is a good book called  learning scala by  Oreilly that I recommend
I don't get any money if you buy it or whatnot but a really good reference and it does go to all those
little details I talked about.
You want to learn more but that's enough to get you started.
I think that's enough for now so let's just start to dive into some actual spark streaming shall we
.
And congratulations.
You now know Scala